Guide to the Cornwall Miscellanea 1779-2003 MS 011 MS 011 MS 011
Cornwall Historical Society
Cornwall Photographs and Miscellanea
1779-2003
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 011
26 Linear Feet (38 Boxes)
This collection is comprised of assorted papers and photographs related to Cornwall residents.
Provenance
The collection was begun by local historian E.C. Starr, and continued by later town historians and Cornwall Historical Society members such as Michael Gannett.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The collection was begun by local historian E.C. Starr and continued by later town historians and Cornwall Historical Society members such as Michael Gannett. Unlike other documents related to individuals and families from Cornwall, these items were not put into occupational categories and were collected mainly for genealogical purposes. Photographs were similarly collected mainly for genealogical purposes and include images related to local families and their homes, along with photographs associated with everyday life in the community.
Scope and Content Note
This Cornwall Photographs and Miscellanea Collection is comprised of four series; photographic materials, people, town materials, and books and miscellanea. The series are divided topically into sections.
The Photographic Materials series is comprised of photographs, photo negatives, slides and tintypes of various Cornwall residents, locations, and events.
The materials in the People series include biographical and genealogical information on various Cornwall residents.
The Town Materials series is comprised of town meeting minutes and annual reports.
The Books and Miscellanea series includes text books, children's books, and religious books.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged topically and then alphabetically and chronologically within each topic.
The files are grouped into 4 series:
Photographic Materials
People
Town Materials
Books and Miscellanea
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Swift, Heman, 1733-1814; Cornwall Historical Society
- Photographic Materials
  - Slides
    - Cornwall Slides 1-120, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      General
      Slides depict various materials from collection.
    - Cornwall Slides 121-139, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Slides of various buildings in West Cornwall and North Cornwall
    - Cornwall Slides 240-339, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Slides of various buildings and landscapes in Cornwall Hollow and Cornwall Bridge
    - Cornwall Slides 360-480, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      Slides of various buildings in Cornwall Plain, East Cornwall, and West Cornwall
    - Cornwall Slides 481-599, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Slides of various buildings and people in West Cornwall, Cornwall Bridge, and Cornwall Plain
    - Cornwall Slides 600-718, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Slides of various people and buildings in West Cornwall, North Cornwall, Cream Hill, and Cornwall Bridge
    - Cornwall Slides 719-838, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Slides of various landscapes and buildings in West Cornwall, Cornwall Bridge, East Cornwall, and Cornwall Plain
    - Cornwall Slides 839-958, 1987-1988 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      Slides of various people and buildings in Cornwall Bridge, West Cornwall, Cornwall Hollow, and Cornwall Village
    - Cornwall Slides 959-1078, 1987-1988 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      Slides of various buildings and people in Cornwall Bridge, West Cornwall, North Cornwall, and Cornwall Hollow
    - Cornwall Slides 1079-1198, 1988-1989 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      Slides of various buildings and people in Cornwall Bridge, West Cornwall, North Cornwall, Cornwall Plain, and Cornwall Hollow
    - Cornwall Slides 1199-1318, 1989-1990 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      Slides of various people and buildings in West Cornwall, Cornwall Hollow, and Cornwall Plain
    - Cornwall Slides 1319-1438, 1990-1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      Slides of various landscapes, people, and buildings in Cornwall Bridge, North Cornwall, West Cornwall, East Cornwall, and Cornwall Hollow
    - Cornwall Slides 1439-1559, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      Slides of various buildings and people in West Cornwall, Cornwall Hollow, North Cornwall, and East Cornwall.
    - Cornwall Slides 1560-1679, 1992-1994 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      Slides of various people and buildings in Cream Hill, Cornwall Hollow, East Cornwall, Cornwall Bridge, and West Cornwall
    - Cornwall Slides 1680-1879, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      Slides of various people and buildings in Cream Hill, North Cornwall, and Cornwall Bridge. Also slides of Gen. John Sedgwick's sword and the exhumation and reburial of Henry Obookiah.
    - Cornwall Slides 1880-1999, N.D. (Box 16, Folder 6)
      Slides of various buildings, people and landscapes from North Cornwall and West Cornwall.
    - Cornwall Slides 2000-2092, 5472, 1967-1998 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      Slides of various people and locations in Cornwall Hollow, West Cornwall, Cornwall Plain, and East Cornwall. Also slides of Henry Obookiah's grave and of World War I-era posters.
    - Arlington Yutzler's 1955 Flood Slides (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Slides of the aftermath of the Flood of 1955 taken by Arlington Yutzler. Most of the slides are from West Cornwall.
    - Cornwall 1976 Slides, 1975-1976 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      Slides of the Cornwall Library Association's Cornwall 1976 Program. This series of color slides was commissioned to coincide with the 1976 Bicentennial and includes images of Cornwall Bridge, Cornwall Plain, West Cornwall, Cornwall Village, and North Cornwall. The images were taken by Mrs. Merrill Prentice and arranged and captioned by Mrs. Kenneth Merz.
    - Slide Index, ca. 1950 (Box OS 5)
      Index comprised of numbered note cards, created ca. 1950, that corresponds to each of the slides in the CHS collection.
    - Kodak Slide Carousel, 1976 (Box OS 8)
  - Photographs
    - Locations
      - Cornwall Bridge
        - Dudleytown Road, 1930 (Box 17, Folder 1)
          Photograph of a one-and-a-half story frame house along Dudleytown Road formerly owned by the Patterson and Nye families.
        - Sandmeyer Properties, circa 1900-1976 (Box 17, Folder 2)
          Photographs of properties owned by the Sandmeyer family, including their farm on Popple Swamp Road and hardware business.
        - Methodist Episcopal Church, circa 1900-1995 (Box 17, Folder 3)
          Photographs of the Methodist Episcopal Church. The building was sold in 1970 and converted into a Masonic lodge.
        - Berkshire Products Co., Inc. Vinegar Factory, circa 1900-circa 1930 (Box 17, Folder 4)
          Photographs of the Berkshire Products Co., Inc. vinegar factory. Images include the extant structure and its demolition.
        - Bennett House, 1927-ca.2000 (Box 17, Folder 5)
          Photographs of the Greek Revival style Bennett House along Popple Swamp Road.
        - Popple Swamp Road, ca. 1890-ca. 2000 (Box 17, Folder 6)
          Photographs of the general area along Popple Swamp Road. Images include miscellaneous landscapes and homes.
        - Housatonic River, circa 1900-1994 (Box 17, Folder 7)
          Photographs of the Housatonic River. Specific images include ice dams and instances of flooding.
        - Train Station, circa 1900-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 8)
          Photographs of the Cornwall Bridge Train Station.
        - Miscellaneous Businesses, circa 1910-1976 (Box 17, Folder 9)
          Photographs of various businesses in Cornwall Bridge, including the Harrison House Inn, the Cornwall Electric Co., the Neoweld Corporation, and the Dairymen's Co-Operative Ass'n, Inc.
        - Engisch Properties, circa 1915 (Box 17, Folder 10)
          Photographs of the home and store owned by Walter and George Engisch. Gift of M. McGowan.
        - Old Covered Bridge, circa 1900-circa 1930 (Box 17, Folder 11)
          Photographs of of the covered bridge across the Housatonic River in Cornwall Bridge. The bridge was destroyed in a flood in March 1936.
        - Iron Bridge, 1930-1998 (Box 17, Folder 12)
          Photographs of the iron bridge across the Housatonic River, constructed in 1930.
          - Iron Bridge, N.D. (Box OS1)
            Eight black and white photographs of the iron bridge matted and mounted on foamcore taken by J. L. Mosher.
          - Iron Bridge, January 1930 (Box OS 3, Folder 21)
            Oversize photograph of the iron bridge over the Housatonic River.
        - Housatonic Valley Rug Shop, circa 1970-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 13)
          Photographs of the Housatonic Valley Rug Shop along Route 7. Images include the building and various employees.
        - Volunteer Fire Department, 1957-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 14)
          Photographs of the fire house in Cornwall Bridge.
        - Cornwall Bridge Iron Company, circa 1890 (Box 17, Folder 15)
          Photograph of the Cornwall Bridge Iron Company works.
        - General Store, circa 1930-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 16)
          Photographs of the general store along Route 7. The store was operated by Monroe and Odell, H.W. Breen, and Ed Baird, respectively.
        - Mills, 1901-circa 1930 (Box 17, Folder 17)
          Photographs of three mills in Cornwall Bridge, namely the Pelletier Mill, Charles Everett's feed mill, and a turning mill. The turning mill and Everett's feed mill stood along Furnace Brook. The photo of the Pelletier mill was donated by John A. Feeney and the photo of the turning mill was donated by A.M. Schillinger. The photo of the Everett mill was taken by Prof. B.S. Dean.
        - Cornwall Inn, circa 1930-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 18)
          Photographs of the Cornwall Inn along Route 7.
        - Landscapes, circa 1910-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 19)
          Photographs of assorted landscapes taken in Cornwall Bridge.
        - Post Office Traffic Accident, November 10, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 20)
          Photographs of the aftermath of a car crashing into the Cornwall Bridge Post Office. Images feature witnesses and first responders.
        - River Road, circa 1940-circa 1990 (Box 17, Folder 21)
          Photographs of three unlabeled houses along River Road.
        - Kent Road, circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 22)
          Photograph of a one-and-a-half story home along Kent Road.
        - Swift's Bridge, 1924-1927 (Box 17, Folder 23)
          Photographs of the Swift's Bridge area of Cornwall Bridge. Images include the bridge for which the area is named, a barn along Swift Bridge Road, and the aftermath of a train derailment.
        - Route 4, circa 1930 (Box 17, Folder 24)
          Photograph of the Benjamin Dean home along Route 4. The structure was built by Dean in 1789 and burned down in 1931.
        - St. Bridget's Church Interior, circa 1940-2003 (Box 17, Folder 25)
          Photographs of the interior of St. Bridget's Church. Photos include images of the altar, organ, baptismal font, and an unspecified wedding.
        - St. Bridget's Church Exterior, circa 1940-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 26)
          Photographs of the exterior of St. Bridget's Church and the immediate surrounding area. Photos include images of the building, the cemetery, and a fire that destroyed the church's barn in 1963.
        - Route 7 Establishments, 1931-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 27)
          Photographs of establishments along Route 7. Images include Nora's Nursery, the Cornwall Package Store, the National Iron Bank, and the Cornwall Bridge Post Office.
        - Route 7 Streetscapes, circa 1922-circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 28)
          Photographs of Route 7. Images include photos donated by Pauline Hayes of the route's 1922 construction and views of the route following a snow storm.
        - Dwellings, circa 1910- circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 29)
          Photographs of assorted homes in Cornwall Bridge. Specific houses include the Cavell/Hayes House and the Swift/Beers House.
        - Miscellaneous, October 21, 1979 (Box 17, Folder 30)
          Photograph of the rock formation painted to look like a frog along Route 7.
        - Housatonic Meadows State Park, circa 2000 (Box 35, Folder 19)
          Photograph of an exhibit on Camp Cross 182 Co., Housatonic Meadows State Park.
        - Aftermath of 1948 Ice Jam, March 18, 1948 (Box 35, Folder 20)
          Photographs of the aftermath of an ice jam on the Housatonic River.
        - Joshua Pierce House, December 10, 1973 (Box 35, Folder 21)
          Photograph of the Paul H. Chamberlain House. The main part of the dwelling was built by Joshua Pierce in 1773.
        - Grist Mill Foundation (Box 35, Folder 29)
          Photograph of a grist mill foundation along the Cornwall River.
        - Alfred S. Dilliston Album, February 1953 (Box 37, Folder 4)
          Photographs taken of Cornwall Bridge by Alfred S. Dilliston while visiting Mr. and Mrs. Clifford Hotchkiss. Images include the Housatonic River, Housatonic Meadows state Park, and the Iron Bridge.
        - Housatonic Meadows State Park, N.D. (Box 35, Folder 19)
          Photograph of an informative poster on Camp Cross 182 Co., Housatonic Meadows State Park.
        - Aftermath of 1948 Ice Jam, March 18, 1948 (Box 35, Folder 20)
          Photographs showing the Housatonic River after an ice jam broke in March 1948.
        - Joshua Pierce House, December 10, 1973 (Box 35, Folder 21)
          Photograph of the home built in 1773 by Joshua Pierce. It was later owned by Paul Chamberlain.
        - Railroad Station Renovation, October 1, 1973 (Box 35, Folder 28)
          Photograph of repairs being made to the railroad station.
        - Grist Mill Foundation (Box 35, Folder 29)
          Photograph of an old grist mill foundation along the Cornwall River.
        - A. S. Dilliston Album, 1953 (Box 37, Folder 4)
          Photographs from the "Tranquility" homestead owned by the Clifford Hotchkiss family in Cornwall Bridge. Photos were taken by Alfred S. Dillistin.
        - Defiance Stove, N.D. (Box 37, Folder 18)
          Photograph of a Defiance model stove from F. Gomez of Cornwall Bridge.
      - Cornwall Center
        - Bunker Hill Road, circa 1940 (Box 17, Folder 31)
          Photograph of the Ives/Tripp House.
        - John R. Harrison House, 1893 (Box 17, Folder 32)
          Photograph of the John R. Harrison House along Route 128. The home was built circa 1840.
        - Prentice-Designed Homes, N.D. (Box 17, Folder 33)
          Photographs of two homes in Cornwall Center designed by T. Merrill Prentice. One stood along Route 4 and the other on Todd Hill Road.
        - Town Sign, circa 1950- circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 34)
          Photographs of the town sign along Route 128.
        - Methodist Episcopal Church, 1911- circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 35)
          Photographs of the Methodist Episcopal Church in Cornwall Center. The structure was built in 1839 near the corner of present-day Route 128 and Todd Hill Road, and was converted into a private residence in the twentieth century. Photos include images of both the exterior and interior of the church, as well as parishoners. There are additional photographs depicting the structure as both a church and dwelling.
        - Landscapes, 1895-1911 (Box 17, Folder 36)
          Photographs of various landscapes around Cornwall Center. Specific images include photos of blossoming apple trees taken by Emily E. Marsh and a pair of locust trees planted by Rev. Hezekiah Gold circa 1760.
        - Ford Farm, 1868 (Box 17, Folder 37)
          Photographs of the Form Farm on Town Street. One photo depicts the rear of the structure, while the other shows Emily S. Ford with her two-year-old son Chauncey in front of the family home. The second photo was donated by Richard S. Ford.
        - Todd Hill Road, circa 1926 (Box 17, Folder 38)
          Photograph depicting a two-story, Greek Revival style home located at 57 Todd Hill Road.
        - Miscellaneous, 1913- circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 39)
          Photographs of unidentified structures in Cornwall Center.
        - Berkshire Country Store, January 1995 (Box 17, Folder 40)
          Photograph of the Berkshire Country Store located at the corner of Route 4, Route 128, and Route 43.
        - Emmons Place, circa 1878 (Box 17, Folder 41)
          Photograph of the Emmons property. In the image, Edward R. White and Abigail Baldwin White are waiting for the mail in front of their home along with Gertrude, Annie, snd Ruth Harrison and Charles S. Leavenworth.
        - George C. Harrison Farm, circa 1870-1913 (Box 17, Folder 42)
          Photographs of George C. Harrison's farm, known as "Plainview." The Italianate structure was built circa 1860, and images include photos of both its exterior and interior, as well as the Harrison family.
        - Doyle's Chevrolet Agency and Garage, 1930 (Box 20, Folder 12)
          Photograph of the filling station and garage operated by the Doyle family at the Four Corners. The building later housed the Berkshire Country Store.
      - North Cornwall
        - O'Donnell Farm, 1936-1995 (Box 18, Folder 1)
          Photographs of the O'Donnell Farm near the corner of Town Street and Cogswell Road. Images include the O'Donnell farmhouse and the process of moving a barn onto the property in 1936. The barn was later converted into the Vizcarrondo home.
        - Brush/Dutton House, 1871-1989 (Box 18, Folder 2)
          Photographs of the Brush/Dutton House on Town Street. The home was first owned by the Brush family and then later by the Duttons.
        - Cogswell Road, 1935- circa 2000 (Box 18, Folder 3)
          Photographs of various properties located along Cogswell Road. Specific images include the Senzer House and the Jessie Rogers House.
        - Landscapes (Box 18, Folder 4)
          Photographs of various landscapes in North Cornwall.
        - Old Burnham Place, N.D. (Box 18, Folder 5)
          Photographs of the former home of Oliver Burnham (1760-1846) on Town Street. The house is shown in various stages of collapse.
        - Ives Farm, circa 1910- circa 1990 (Box 18, Folder 6)
          Photographs of the Ives family farm on Town Street. Images include photos of the interior and exterior of the farm house as well as family members performing farm work.
        - Scoville Farm, 1871-1989 (Box 18, Folder 7)
          Photographs of the Ives family farm on Town Street. Images include views of farmland, photos of various structures on the property, and farm work.
        - Rogers Farm, 1897- circa 1930 (Box 18, Folder 8)
          Photographs of the Rogers family farm on Town Street. Specific images include the Col. Anson Rogers Home, the Dwight Rogers Home, and the Noah Rogers Home.
        - Scoville Road, N.D. (Box 18, Folder 9)
          Photographs of an unspecified home on Scoville Road.
        - Rattlesnake Road, N.D. (Box 18, Folder 10)
          Photographs of unspecified houses on Rattlesnake Road.
        - North Cornwall Meeting House Exterior, circa 1900-1989 (Box 18, Folder 11)
          Photographs of the exterior of the North Cornwall Meeting House. The church was founded in 1782 as the Second Congregational Church and the current building dates to 1826.
        - North Cornwall Meeting House Interior, circa 1926 (Box 18, Folder 12)
          Photographs of the interior of the North Cornwall Meeting House. Images include the altar, organ, and pews.
        - North Cornwall Meeting House Events, 1905-1943 (Box 18, Folder 13)
          Photographs of various social events that took place at the North Cornwall Meeting House including a 1905 gathering photographed by James Henry Moser and images from the building's centennial in 1926.
        - North Cornwall Meeting House Renovations, 1951-1978 (Box 18, Folder 14)
          Photographs of maintenance work done on the North Cornwall Meeting House. Specific images include photos of work being done on the steeple taken by the Pratt-Reuman family and pictures of the building being painted taken by Dorothy I. Russ in 1978.
        - Town Street, circa 1900-circa 2000 (Box 18, Folder 15)
          Photographs of various homes along Town Street. Specific images include the Ed Bourne/Ellis House, the Dutton House, the Joe Ellis Home, the James Henry Moser Home, and the Bragan House, which was originally the barn of Oliver Burnham.
        - Miscellaneous, 1926-1989 (Box 18, Folder 16)
          Photographs of unlabeled structures and an image depicting the road to Mill Hill sent to Jessie C. Rogers in 1926.
        - 7 Cents House, N.D. (Box 35, Folder 23)
          Photograph of the "7 Cents House" amid flood waters.
        - Seven Cents House, N.D. (Box 35, Folder 23)
          Photograph of the home known as the "7 Cents House."
        - Pratt Farm, circa 1914 (Box 37, Folder 17)
          Photograph of the Pratt property taken from Rattlesnake Road.
        - Scoville House, N.D. (Box 21, Folder 14)
          Photographs of the Scoville property on Town Street. The home was owned by the Prudhomme family by 1976.
      - Cream Hill
        - Pratt Farm, circa 1900- circa 1914 (Box 18, Folder 17)
          Photographs of the Pratt family farm on Cream Hill Road. Images include photos of farm buildings, farm work, and family members, as well as a milk delivery man.
        - Cherry Hill, 1925 (Box 18, Folder 18)
          Photographs of various houses on Cherry Hill. Specified images include 272 Cream Hill Road and 280 Cream Hill Road.
        - Horace Hart Property, N.D. (Box 18, Folder 19)
          Photographs of the Horace Hart property.
        - Hart Hill Farm, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 20)
          Photograph of Hart Hill Farm taken during the summer of 1989.
        - Gold Family Properties, circa 1900- circa 2000 (Box 18, Folder 21)
          Photographs of property owned by the Gold family on Cream Hill. Specific images include photographs of the Cream Hill Agricultural School, photos of the T.S. Gold House later owned by Ted and Ralph Gold, and an image of the James Douglas Home, which was built in 1750 and remained in the Gold family for generations. A collection of photographs of farm animals taken by Michael Gannett is also present.
        - Cream Hill Road, N.D. (Box 18, Folder 22)
          Photographs of various properties located along Cream Hill Road. Specific images include the home of Rose Algrant at 163 Cream Hill Road and Harry Root's house.
        - Cole/Fishman House, 1946-1989 (Box 18, Folder 23)
          Photographs of the Cole/Fishman House, located at the intersection of Cream Hill Road, Cherry Hill Road, and Cogswell Road.
        - Cornwall Childcare Center, January 1995 (Box 18, Folder 24)
          Photographs of the recently-completed Cornwall Childcare Center on Cream Hill Road.
        - Gannett Property, circa 1930-1992 (Box 18, Folder 25)
          Photographs of the Gannett property. Specific photos include the Lewis Gannett Home later owned by W. Goldberg and a photograph of the studio barn taken by Michael Gannett.
        - Douglas House, N.D. (Box 18, Folder 26)
          Copy of a photograph of the James Douglas House. The structure is pictured in the background of a photograph of T.S. Gold. The home was built by the settler James Douglas in 1750 and stood as the oldest home in town until it was torn down in the 1950s.
        - Cream Hill Farm, 1989-1995 (Box 18, Folder 27)
          Photographs of Cream Hill Farm, located along Cream Hill Road.
        - Rexford Road/Lane, N.D. (Box 18, Folder 28)
          Photographs of unlabeled properties located along Rexford Road, alternately known as Rexford Lane.
        - Scoville Road, circa 1870-1989 (Box 19, Folder 1)